Today I'm going to make Salt and Straws
salted molted chocolate chip cookie
dough, which is the longest ice cream
name in the universe.
So, there's quite a bit in this recipe.
I found this recipe years ago when I
made it originally on the channel. Um,
it was one of my favorite ice creams
I've ever made. So, you know, Salt and
Straw, they do make some good ice
creams. Their recipe books are kind of,
you know, they're okay, but some turn
out really wonky, and that's just
because they use this generic base. You
don't need any fancy ingredients, but
there is a bit to do. So, what are we
going to need for the ice cream base?
For salt and straw, salted molted
chocolate chip cookie dough ice cream
base. Man, that takes forever to say,
you're going to need 620 g of whole
milk, 495
g of cream, 33% to 36%, 200 g of sugar,
92 g of molasses,
12 g of glucose or corn syrup or golden
syrup, 68 g of skim milk powder, and 12
g of vanilla extract. Yeah. So, the base
for this is a molasses vanilla ice
cream. Big fan of molasses flavor. So,
why don't we get everything going and
get that ice cream base made before we
move on to the other parts. So, we're
going to start with 620 g of whole milk,
495 g of cream,
12 g of glucose syrup or corn syrup, and
then molasses.
92 g
200 g of sugar. We're putting this into
a container so we can mix in our
stabilizer.
68 g of skim milk powder. I might as
well just pour that in.
1.5 g of guar gum or guum if you're in
the US. We're going to stir all of those
powders together. If you want to use
zantham gum, you absolutely can. That is
fine. So, with our powders mixed
together, we can put all of that into
there. And
we're going to whisk that together. It
will only take a minute or two of
whisking to dissolve that sugar and to
dissipate the molasses and the corn
syrup. So, just give it a couple of
minutes, a minute or two, and it'll all
be ready to go.
Man, I couldn't get that lid off.
Finally, 12 g
of vanilla extract. Let's take 2 and 1/2
teaspoons, you know, but all cup
measurements are in the description.
It's going to go straight into the
refrigerator and we're going to leave it
in there overnight cuz we want those
flavors to develop. Yep, we're good to
go. That is now going to go in the
refrigerator overnight and we can look
at the cookie doughs and the molted
fudge.
For the molted cookie dough, you are
going to need 60 gram of unsalted butter
at room temperature, 30 g of sugar, 55 g
of brown sugar, 5 g of salt, 30 g of
cream, 5 g of molasses, 15 g of corn
syrup, 5 g of vanilla extract, 60 g of
allpurpose or plain flour,
30 g of malt powder and 50 g of semieet
chocolate chips. First thing we're going
to do is take 60 g of allpurpose flour,
plain flour, and we're going to bake it
in the oven at 350 fahhe, which is this
in centigrade for 10 minutes. And that
is on their instruction. It's to kill
all the pathogens within the flour if
there are any, so it's safe to use. If
you're wondering why there's cake back
there, then don't forget to head over to
my other channel where I make lots of
chocolates, bon bonss, fancy desserts. I
have recently trained as a chocolier and
I'm now starting the training as a
pastry chef. So, make sure to head head
over to my new channel. Don't forget to
like and subscribe. So, with our flour
in the oven, bacon off at 350 for 10
minutes, let's get everything else ready
so we can assemble our molted cookie
dough. So, the first thing we're going
to do is get our butter into this
container.
60 g.
Then goes our 30 g of normal sugar, 55 g
of brown sugar,
and our salt. We're going to cream that
together, break up any of those lumps of
brown sugar, and then we'll come back
and add the rest ingredients. So, with
all of that creamed together, we can add
in our cream, which is 30 g. Our
vanilla, which is 5 g, our molasses,
which is also 5 g. Our corn syrup, you
can use glucose syrup, you can use
honey, you can use golden syrup, which
is 15 g. And we're going to stir that
together.
In goes our malt powder. I'm going to
use original Holix this time. You can
use actual
dry malt extract.
You can use Ovaltine, not the chocolate
version because you don't want to add
chocolate flavor to this. Let me get
this open. Holix reminds me of England.
Uh I love Holix. It's just a really nice
comforting
drink in a winter's evening. On a
winter's evening. We're going to stir
that together. And now we've got that.
We're going to leave that now. I'm going
to take the flour out the oven that's
been in there for 10 minutes. We're
going to let that cool down. Otherwise,
it's going to melt everything into a
mess. So, we leave this here for about
10 minutes. And while we wait for that
to cool down, I'm going to eat some of
this cake which is over there. Right.
And with our flour cooled down enough,
that's going in there.
And going to stir that together.
Finally, our chocolate chips. about 50
grams, but you know, you can put as many
as you like in. Let's get a bit of
kitchen foil molted cookie dough
out in here.
And that
is going to go into the refrigerator now
until tomorrow when we're going to chop
it up into cubes.
Onto the molted fudge. For the molted
fudge, you're going to need 15 g of cold
water, 10 gram of malt powder, 110 g of
corn syrup, 120 g of heavy cream, 15 g
of unsalted butter, 1 g of salt, 20 g of
cocoa powder, and 85 g of chopped
chocolate. We need to add in to a little
small pot 1 tbsp of water, and two
teaspoon of malt powder. You can
actually add a lot more malt powder to
this. So that's what I'm going to do.
So there's our 1 tbsp of water. I'm
going to add in
that much, which is basically three
times what they say. So I'm going to add
that in there. If you use dry milk
extract, then you might want to reduce
it a little bit because, you know, some
people don't like it that strong. I do.
Going to stir that together.
just to hydrate that powder. Now comes
the kicker for their fudge. Their fudge
requires 110 g of corn syrup. So that's
going in here as well. Again, you can
use golden syrup or glucose. So, but I'm
going to use corn syrup cuz that's what
their recipe calls for. 110 g. There's a
lot. 120 g of cream.
1/4 of a teaspoon of salt. and 1 tbspoon
of butter. We're going to get this on
the heat until it comes to a gentle
boil. So that means the butter's melted
and everything is stirred together
nicely and just starting to boil. So
that's what we're going to do. There we
go. We've just come to the boil.
Everything has melted nice. So we're
going to put in our chocolate.
Stir that. That can just kind of sit
there and melt.
and one fat tablespoon of cocoa powder,
15 g if you want to want to weigh it,
but
doesn't need to be exact. These cookie
dough recipes, you can put more cocoa
powder in as long as you're not, you
know, tripling the amount. That would be
silly cuz you're just going to dry the
the fudge out. Um, you know, you can put
more malt powder in. You can play with
it. If you want your fudge a bit
thinner, then add more cream. If you
want a bit thicker, then obviously
reduce the the amount of cream. As our
chocolate has now melted. If you've got
a chocolate bar, chop up that chocolate.
If you're using chocolate chips, just
put it in. I'm using couvet to chocolate
cuz obviously I used that on the other
channel. I'm going to finish it off with
a tiny whisk. Make sure that cocoa
powder is completely broken down. Let's
get a container and pour that into
there.
And that can now go in the refrigerator
again overnight. Cookie dough and the
fudge will keep for ages.
It says a week on the recipe, but in my
experience, it keeps for at least twice
that. So that's going to go in the
fridge until tomorrow as well. So that's
everything ready until tomorrow. So So
let's cut to Tuesday. This week's video
is sponsored by Yol. And thankfully,
it's an easy one for me because I use
one of their bikes to maintain this
really less than adequate form of
fitness that I have. Connecting your
YOLO G1M
Plus bike couldn't be easier. You simply
open the YOLO app, tap connect, and the
bike pairs instantly. No searching, no
waiting. Once it's connected, all your
live metrics appear clearly on the
screen. cadence, resistance levels,
calories burned, everything you need to
stay on track. But the real magic is
Yaso's workout library. The app has a
huge range of classes, hit classes,
scenic routes, low impact spins, and
structured training sessions. They guide
you, motivate you, and help you reach
your goals. And here's the part that
makes it even better. The Pelaton app
connects seamlessly. Just open the
Pelaton app, start a ride. The metrics
sync up perfectly. You get the Pelaton
classes with the precision data from
your G1M Plus. No fuss. Only the screen
adapter that comes with your bike is
required. And yes, it gets even better.
The KOM app, which is my app of choice,
connects just as simply. One tap,
instant pairing. The bike metrics
display right in the live route. Whether
you're cycling through the Alps, coastal
roads, or forest trails, you can choose
the original speed or fully interactive.
So, the ride changes depending on your
skill level. So, when it's minus 19
Celsius outside, the snow is piling up
and the streets are frozen, you're still
riding. You can climb snowy mountains,
push through the scenic winter roots,
all within the warmth and comfort of
your own home on the YOL G1M Plus bike.
>> Shift to 24% resistance.
>> Again, a big thank you to Yol for
sponsoring this video. Back to the ice
cream. So, with our ice cream base
completely chilled in the fridge, we're
going to give it a quick stir together.
Just make sure it's completely
homogenized before it goes in our pre-
chilled ice cream machine. Now, we're
going to chop up the cookie dough into
whatever size pieces you like. I'm just
doing little cubes. And your fudge is
going to need working together cuz it's
pretty stiff. So, give it a really good
stir to loosen it up. Then out come with
a classic tub. I mean, I've had these
tubs for years. But right at the end of
the churn, I'm going to put some of that
cookie dough in and let the machine spin
around. If your machine isn't strong
enough, just stir it in by hand and
start loading up your tubs a couple of
spoonfuls at a time. Then followed by a
really good helping of that fudge. A few
extra cookie dough pieces if you really
want to. Or you do. And then finish
loading up the tubs for putting it in
the freezer to harden off just for a few
hours.
It looks delicious. Time to scoop.
Salt and Straws salted molted chocolate
chip cookie dough. I used the original
Holix for the malt flavor in this this
time as opposed to malt extract that I
used last time. I think it's been a long
time since I made it. Um it weird enough
I remember Holix smelling stronger.
It doesn't
you have to really get your nose in
there. Um, it it does smell, but it
tastes just as strong as I remember. I
love Holix. Um, like a proper old fart.
Scooped really nicely. The fudge has a
touch of ice in it. This This is not my
recipe for the fudge. This is Salt and
Straws recipe. If it were me personally,
I would just adjust it slightly so that
it's a little less icy. But looking
forward to trying this one again. Let's
dig in.
It's still as good as I remember. The
tiny bit of iciness in that fudge
doesn't distract from the ice cream at
all. It's such a good combination. That
malty flavor from the Holix shining
through with that. Also, that that
molted cookie dough is delicious. Don't
skimp on the chocolate chips either cuz
that adds a really nice alternate
texture here. You've got the bite of the
cookie dough, the bite of those
chocolate chips. Super delicious creamy
ice cream with that fudge note at the
end. Oh, it's good. I made a very small
batch here. Not I made one and a half
kilo batch. Uh it got me
2 L in the Miso 4080.
Um, you know, so that kind of gives you
an idea of overrun numbers. Make this
into Ninja Creamy, you're going to have
to stir the add-ins in. So, make the
base, spin it up, stir the cookie dough
in, stir that fudge in after. If you're
making in a creamy, you're likely going
to have to just heat up that fudge, that
malt fudge just a little bit to to
enable swirling it around cuz it's quite
a thick fudge. Super [snorts] super nice
this one. Thanks very much everyone for
watching, liking, subscribing. Next
week, coffee, coffee, buzz, buzz, buzz.
It's super cold next week. We got a cold
[music] front coming through. A cold
front's middle winter in Alberta, so
it's cold. We got a cold front coming
through. So, it's minus 22 centrade. So,
I'm going to take some ice cream outside
and spin it and see how quick I can
freeze it. So, if you want to see how
that goes, hit subscribe. See you guys
next week.